Guillaume Jaume

≈ +41-78-661-4152 ⊠ guillaume.jaume@epfl.ch in guillaume-jaume 🞖 Guillaume Jaume 🗘 guillaumejaume

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research focuses on deep learning for graph-structured data with applications to computational pathology. I developed graph-based representations and models of histopathological tissues, notably by leveraging Graph Neural Networks. Specifically, I have explored three lines of research in computational pathology: scalability, explainability and weakly supervised settings.

EDUCATION

• Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering

Jan 2018 - Jan 2022

IBM Research, Zurich & EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland Thesis: Graph Representation Learning in Computational Pathology

Advisors: Prof. Dr. Jean-Philippe Thiran; Dr. Maria Gabrani

- M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering & Information Technology

Sep 2015 - Sep 2017

EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

Thesis: A Cognitive Solution to Extract and Understand Information in Medical Forms (GPA 6/6)

• Erasmus exchange, Electrical & Computer Engineering Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh, United Kingdom Sep 2014 - June 2015

• B.Sc. in Electrical Engineering

Sep 2012 - June 2015

EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

WORK EXPERIENCE

• Harvard Medical School, Boston, United-States

From May 2022

Post-doctoral research fellow at Mahmood Lab – Brigham's Women's Hospital Focus: Scalable Computational Pathology, Biomarker Discovery

• IBM Research Zurich, Switzerland

Dec 2017 - Fev 22

Pre-doctoral researcher in the Cognitive Healthcare & Life Sciences group

Focus: Computational Pathology, Graph Representation Learning

Collaborators: ETH Zurich, Mayo Clinic, CHUV Lausanne, University Hospital of Zurich, University Hospital of Paris, University of Bern, National Research Council of Italy

• EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

Sep 2014 - Jun 2016

Teaching Assistant with Prof. Dr. Nicolas Macris & Prof. Dr. Andreas Burg Focus: Supervise students in practicals, projects and labs

· CERN, Geneva, Switzerland

June 2015 - Aug 2015

CERN Summer Student Program, High-Luminosity LHC

Project: Development of 3D automation tools for Radio Frequency measurements

PUBLICATIONS

Journals:

• P. Pati*, <u>G. Jaume</u>*, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez et al., "Hierarchical Graph Representations in Digital Pathology," Medical Image Analysis, 2021 [arXiv] [Code]

Conferences & Workshops:

 $^{^*}$ denotes equal contribution

- <u>G. Jaume</u>*, P. Pati*, B. Bozorgtabar et al., "Quantifying Explainers of Graph Neural Networks in Computational Pathology," IEEE CVPR, 2021 [arXiv] [Code]
- V. Anklin*, P. Pati*, <u>G. Jaume</u>* et al., "Learning Whole-Slide Segmentation from Inexact and Incomplete Labels using Tissue Graphs," MICCAI, 2021 [arXiv] [Code]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>*, P. Pati*, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez et al., "HistoCartography: A Toolkit for Graph Analytics in Digital Pathology," MICCAI Compay Workshop, 2021 [arXiv] [Code] [Best Software Paper Award]
- P. Pati*, <u>G. Jaume</u>*, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez et al., "HACT-Net: A Hierarchical Cell-to-Tissue Graph Neural Network for Histopathological Image Classification," MICCAI, Graphs in Biomedical Image Analysis Workshop, 2020 [arXiv] [Best paper award]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>*, P. Pati*, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez et al., "Towards Explainable Graph Representations in Digital Pathology," ICML, Computational Biology Workshop, 2020 [arXiv] [Best paper award]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>, H. Ekenel, J-P. Thiran, "FUNSD: A Dataset for Form Understanding in Noisy Scanned Documents," IEEE ICDAR, 2019 [arXiv] [Website]
- G. Jaume, A. Nguyen, M. Martinez et al., "edGNN: A simple and powerful GNN for labeled graphs," ICLR, Representation Learning on Graphs and Manifolds Workshop, 2019 [arXiv] [Code]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>, B. Bozorgtabar, H. Ekenel et al., "Image-Level Attentional Context Modeling Using Nested-Graph Neural Networks," NeurIPS, Relational Representation Learning Workshop, 2018 [arXiv]

Book chapters:

• P. Pati*, <u>G. Jaume</u>*, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez, et al., "Graph Representation Learning & Explainability in Breast Cancer Pathology: Bridging the gap between AI and Pathology Practice," Artificial Intelligence as applied in Human Pathology, Editor: R. Huss, World Scientific, 2021

Preprints:

- <u>G. Jaume</u>*, P. Pati*, et al., "Weakly Supervised Learning for Joint Whole-Slide Segmentation and Classification in Prostate Cancer," 2021
- N. Brancati,..., <u>G. Jaume</u>, et al., "BRACS: A Dataset for BReAst Carcinoma Subtyping in H&E Histology Images," 2021

LIBRARY & DATASETS

- **HistoCartography**: A collection of image-to-graph translation and state-of-the-art graph algorithms for facilitating interpretable entity-based analysis in digital pathology [Code]
- BReAst Carcinoma Subtyping (BRACS): A large cohort of H&E stained histopathological images for automated breast cancer diagnosis [Website]
- FUNSD: A dataset for Form Understanding in Noisy Scanned Documents [Website]

PATENTS

- P. Pati, <u>G. Jaume</u>, K. Thandiackal, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez, M. Gabrani, "Registration Free Multimodal Digital Pathology," 2021 [Filed]
- P. Pati, <u>G. Jaume</u>, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez, M. Gabrani, "AI agent to assist pathology whole slide image interpretation through hierarchical representations," 2021 [Filed]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez, M. Gabrani, "Extracting structured information from a document containing filled form images," 2019 [Granted]
- <u>G. Jaume</u>, A. Foncubierta-Rodriguez, M. Gabrani, "Method and system for extracting information from an image of a filled form document," 2019 [Granted]

AWARDS

AWARDS	
• Nominated for the EPFL Doctorate Award	Jan 2022
• IBM Outstanding Technical Achievement and Innovation Award "Intelligent and quantitative immunostaining of tumor tissue sections"	May 202.
 IBM First Invention Plateau Best Paper Awards: 	June~202.
• MICCAI, Computational Pathology (COMPAY) Workshop	Sep 202.
• MICCAI, Graphs in Biomedical Image Analysis Workshop	Oct 2020
• ICML, Computational Biology Workshop	July 2020
STUDENT SUPERVISION	
• Valentin Anklin, <i>Master's thesis</i> "Learning Segmentation in Histology from Inexact and Incomplete Labels using GNN	Autumn 2020
• Lauren Alisha Fernandez, <i>Master's thesis</i> "Cell-graph Networks for Representation and Grading of Histopathology Images"	Autumn 2019
• Atul Kumar, <i>Master's thesis</i> "Learning to generate Scene Graphs from Images and vice-versa"	Autumn 2019
• Martin Svatos, Research internship "Mind the Logit Gap: Incomparable Tasks in Continual Learning"	Spring 2019
• Maria Halushko, Research internship "Text Detection in Noisy Scanned Documents"	Autumn 2018
COMMUNITY SERVICE	
Workshop Co-organizer:	
• IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (ISBI), <i>Kolkata</i> "BRIGHT: BReast tumor Image classification on Gigapixel HisTopathological image	March 2022 es"
• American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA), San Diego "Workshop on Explainable Multimodal AI in Cancer Patient Care"	Nov 202
• Applied Machine Learning Days (AMLD), Lausanne "Building Interpretable AI for Digital Pathology" [Code]	April 202
• Talks:	
- Symposium on Dig Path in the DACH Region, $Bern$ – Invited by Prof. Inti Zlobek "Graph Representation Learning in Computational Pathology"	Feb 2022
• Tissue Image Analytics Centre, Warwick – Invited by Prof. Nasir Rajpoot "HistoCartography: Graph representations and models in Computational Pathology	Oct 202.
 Charité University Hospital, Berlin "Graph Representations and Models in Digital Pathology" 	Oct 202.
- PathAI, $New\ York$ "Weakly-Supervised Learning for Whole-Slide-Image Segmentation"	July 202.
• Harvard Medical School, <i>Boston</i> – Invited by Prof. Faisal Mahmood "A Graph Network Tour of Computational Pathology"	July 202.
• Lausanne University Hospital (CHUV), Lausanne "Computational Pathology: Building Interpretable AI at Scale"	May 202.
- Swiss Digital Pathology Consortium (SDiPath), $Bern$ "Graph Representation Learning & Explainability in Computational Pathology"	Jan 202.

• Computer Research Institute of Montreal (CRIM), *Montreal* "Deep Learning on Graphs: An Overview" [Code]

Nov 2020

• 10+ Internal IBM Talks, *Zurich* IBM Research, IBM Watson, IBM Global Business Services

2019-2021

• Reviewer: IEEE CVPR, Medical Image Analysis

REFERENCES

• Prof. Dr. Jean-Philippe Thiran Full Professor, EPFL, Lausanne jean-philippe.thiran@epfl.ch

• Prof. Dr. Inti Zlobek Head of Translational Research Unit, University of Bern inti.zlobec@pathology.unibe.ch

• Dr. Pierre Moulin Project Lead IMI BigPicture, Novartis, Basel pierre.moulin@novartis.com